so now that we know that the program
generates virtual addresses but the
processor needs physical addresses to
access the actual memory let's see how
the processor does the virtual to
physical address
translation so the program generates a
virtual address this is what the load
for example will compute as its address
the processor divides this address into
the page offset part which tells us
where in a page we are and the virtual
page number which which tells us which
page in the process are we talking about
if we have a 4 kilobyte page 12 bits are
telling us where in the page we are and
the remaining bits are telling us what
the page number is so let's consider the
address FC 519 08b which is a 32-bit
address the least significant 12 bits
are telling us where in the 4 kilobyte
page we are so that's the page offset
the more significant
bits are telling us what the virtual
page number is now what happens is we
take the virtual page number and use it
as an index into the page table in this
case the index into the page table will
be FC 519 so we find the entry with that
index what that entry tells us is what
the frame number is that corresponds to
this virtual page number that is where
the did we put that page in the actual
physical memory let's say that the frame
number in this entry is
0152 we take this physical frame number
and put it together with the page offset
into a physical address and that is what
we use to actually access the physical
memory in this example the physical
address is composed of the frame number
and the page offset so this is a 32-bit
physical address that we will use to
access the memory note that the page
offset is present in both the virtual
and the physical address so from the
virtual address the least significant
bits that correspond to the page offset
do not change when we translate into the
physical address but the virtual page
number does change because it gets
translated into the frame number